software engineering radio episode 5
model-driven software development
[Music]
hey everybody thanks for listening to
this new episode of software engineering
radio before we actually get started
with monitoring software development I
want to mention a couple of other things
first of all we want to encourage you to
give us feedback we need to know what
you think about the topics we talked
about but the level of detail should we
provide more overview or more more
specific details which topics they want
to hear about in future episodes and who
do you think we should talk about who
should we interview so you can help us
make this a good program by giving us
feedback what you want to hear also I
want to refer you to two other podcasts
first of all Frank Westphal has released
a new episode in his tone up named a
podcast series this is a German podcast
so it might not be interesting for all
of you but after I think five months of
waiting his newest episode released I
think on Monday this week has Tomas
posted and revealed them and talk about
their experience and also their new book
about Ruby on Rails another podcast you
should listen to if you're in the java
world is that java at java
comm that is java POS SEO calm they
provide weekly episodes that give you
the latest updates on news in the java
community they also have from time to
time interviews with celebrities in the
java world for example they had Jonathan
Schwartz the CEO of Sun on their show I
think having software engineering radio
on the one hand side that gives you the
fundamentals of software engineering why
and also having a newscast on your
specific platform on the other side is a
really great combination so if you know
about newscasts for other platforms such
as Microsoft net or Ruby then let us
know so we can point everybody else to
those podcasts so after this rather
lengthy introduction let's now get
started with the topic of this episode
which is brought to you by Marcos and
Everhart note that we had to cut this
discussion into two parts because
otherwise it would have been too
so the next episode of the software
engineering radio podcast will feature
part two of this discussion so in this
episode we are going to talk about
modern software development and how it
makes life easier for software
developers so my initial question is
which are the basic concepts and how do
they fit together so the basic idea of
modern software development is to make
the development efforts more
domain-specific so if you develop in the
banking field then you might want to use
banking specific abstractions when
building your software and if you work
in the Radio Astronomy field for example
and then you might want to use
abstractions that are specific to that
domain so instead of requiring
developers to manually or mentally do
the transition from the main concepts
down to the software technology concepts
all the time when they're programming
the idea is to provide them with more
domain-specific abstractions and let
tools transformers generators - the yeah
the transformation down to the software
artifacts just I don't know Java code or
or ejv or something like that so and in
order to do that you need a number of
things that aren't usually used in like
traditional software development one is
obviously the model a model resides in
the center of all this of this model and
development universe that's why it's
called model driven development and
models in that sense are and that's
important our formal models so formal
means that tools can actually work with
them tools know how to process models so
those models have to have clearly
defined meaning which means they have to
have a defined structure you have to
express them in a well-defined way and
also the semantics is important to
define so in order to come up with those
with these formal models we need a
modeling language that has those
concepts inherently built in and usually
general-purpose modeling languages like
UML are not formal enough so if you have
UML diagram it's quite hard to to
no specifically what it means in order
to generate artifacts from it so what
you usually do is you come up with a DSL
domain-specific language or others call
it domain-specific modeling language
that means you analyze your domain and
you come up with the core concepts of
that domain and you model their
relationships and their properties and
their mere semantics in the most extreme
case usually semantics aren't modeled
formally they're just described but what
you do is you build a meta model and the
meta model defines the construct that
developers can use for modeling so to
make that a bit more concrete if you
look at the UML as an example for
modeling language people can use
concepts such as class Association
attribute operation to build their own
models like you have a class person with
the attribute name and first name in
order to to formally define what a class
is you need to have a meta model and
that meta model contains exactly those
elements that you'll use for modeling
later and in the next stage basically so
things like class Association
generalization attribute operation are
elements of the metamodel
and that means that people who build
instances of the meta model the model
define instances of those meta model
concepts so if I built a model based on
UML I can create an instance of the
metamodel concept class and associate
assign its name to be person and then I
instantiate an object of type attribute
which I call name and which has the type
such-and-such string usually and then I
can create a relationship between the
class and the attribute relay or a
relationship that could be called like
owns and that means that the class owns
the attribute name so that that's the
basic idea another thing you need to
come up with when building your
domain-specific language is the concrete
syntax so the meta model defines the
concepts you use in the language they're
abstract there's no it doesn't say how
those concepts are represented it the
metamodel doesn't say that UML classes
are rectangles with these several
compartments
the concrete syntax does that so if you
build a domain-specific language you
have to define the metamodel
as well as the concrete syntax and that
concrete syntax can be graphical or
textual that's important to really note
all this MDA discussion will catch up
with that later people always think in
graphical models and that's certainly
one option but it's not the only one
once you have the model built on your
DSL you have to make sure that the model
is actually used in some way we don't
want to put the model in a shelf and
look at it just for documentation
purposes because that would be you know
the the old style and nobody does that
voluntarily so the idea is to transform
those models into something that's
executable and to do that you need to
have something called model
transformation that is basically a
technique to transform one model into
another there can be several steps like
you can transform one model into another
model and you can transform that model
into yet another model and once you did
that you can finally transform that that
last model in the chain into code of
course you can also generate you know in
one step directly from your model into
the executable code it's basically a
question of modularization whether you
want to have one step or several step
transformation so the final step of all
that transformation stuff is almost
always code generation okay so to sum up
basically as a developer you use you
build models that are domain-specific so
for example that contain contracts and
whatever you have in your domain and
this is expressed in the domain-specific
language so technically speaking the
domain-specific language defines what
you can do in your model and the
representation can be either textual or
graphically it's not limited in any way
and at the end of the day the semantics
or the real meaning of these models are
expressed in a generator the question is
how this all can be used in in a project
environment and what the benefits are so
can you give an example about a concrete
implementation of such model driven
software development in
project context in one project the idea
was to use model driven development to
simplify working with a potentially
complex architecture now I'm going to
evaluate elaborate later on the
difference between what we call
architectural or architectural centric
model driven development and and non
architectural centric but the idea was
this architecture was built from things
like components long-running business
processes interfaces contracts between
those components we had to manage things
like versioning so we had to know that
if we replace a component with a new
version of that component we had to make
sure that the system still worked and
you know not at runtime but we had to
know this statically so we had to do
things like dependency analysis also we
had to deploy the logic the business
logic on to several different execution
platforms like one of them was spring
another one was the Eclipse framework so
what we did was we came up with a meta
model that captured the core
architectural abstractions in that case
this were things like components
interfaces operations the component
instances their relationships the
process definitions and you know all
these kinds of things so technical
aspects so in what developers then did
was they used a UML tool in that case to
come up with the model so they used
class diagrams with stereotypes to
define what components are and their
interfaces and the relationships between
the components actually what they used
was a UML profile that was built on top
of our domain-specific meta model and
then we use cogeneration to come up with
the concrete implementation so people
would draw their component structure in
the UML diagram generate base classes
from that actually it was a Java project
so they generated Java code and then
they inherited from that generated base
class and into that inherited class they
added the business logic so we didn't
try to express the business logic with
this domains
specific or architectural centric MDS D
approach what we did was that we modeled
the business processes with um also we
used humor slate charts to come up with
the business processes and then we
generated from those UML diagrams the
artifacts that would be used by the
process engine to to execute the process
we did two things we first we used the
jbpm
process engine so we generated the XML
input files and later we generated
native implementations of those date
machines because we thought that was
simpler overall so that was one example
of a project so what you're saying is
there are basic concepts like components
or business processes or whatever that
ever used as a basis for code generation
and what I'm honoring now is this is not
domain-specific in any way because it's
not something that is specific to the
domain that we tackled in this in this
project it's rather something that shows
up in every project more or less because
every project has some kind of
components and there are some kind of
business processes that you are trying
to model so and and it's not specific to
say insurance or banking this really
what driven software development is this
really a domain-specific language or
what is it
there are various flavors of model
driven development one is what we call
architectural centric model driven
development so that domain for which we
built domain-specific languages models
and all that stuff is the architecture
of our system so the metamodel contains
those rather technical concepts such as
component interface contract whatever
and the idea is to make working with
this architecture simpler to generate
glue code automatically to you know make
sure that the programming the business
logic containers components are not you
know you don't have all those angled
brackets everywhere from all the XML and
you know all those invasive programming
models from the various platforms so the
idea is to keep make programming with a
technical platform easier and also
by formalizing your project architecture
into a meta model this actually helps
you come up with a well-defined
architecture because you have to think
about your architecture thoroughly and
clearly define what your you know what
your things in the PowerPoint
presentation actually mean and by doing
that by trying to come up with such of
such a formalized architectural
metamodel your architecture is refined
it actually gets better by doing that we
sometimes say that model driven
development in used in that way is acts
as a kind of architectural catalyst
because it helps you come up with a
better architecture and that in this
specific project this was very obvious
the people at our customer had more or
less big problem to really get started
they they did various specific
collaborations but they didn't you know
they didn't weren't able to come up with
a blueprint for the system and starting
doing this model room and stuff really
out there so this is the architectural
centric model room development of course
you can also try to abstract really
domain-specific concepts now domain not
being the technical aspects of your
system but rather things like insurance
contracts validity constraints for all
kinds of functional or non-technical
things in your system you can do that
however what I always recommend is that
you should start with the architecture
centric thing because if you want to
abstract business concepts then you have
to really understand your business
concepts very well and usually as a
technical person who tries to learn you
know all those model different tools and
all that new stuff it's good if you do
this based on a domain that you know
relatively well and that's at least I
hope that is the architecture so by
starting with architecture centric model
development you kind of get rid of the
problem of understanding deeply a domain
you don't yet know rather you you start
with with your architecture as being the
domain and then once you did that you
can cascade additional layers of dsls on
top of that I mean that's probably
something that's maybe too advanced for
this for this introductory podcast on
that topic but the idea is to use model
transformations to for example model
things like a component that verifies
business contracts or
insurance contracts and then you
generate these basic artifacts from that
but but again that's that's something we
should discuss maybe in a subsequent
episode so what you're saying is that a
one specific domain that you can use in
modern software development is the
architecture of a computing system and
this is one of the things that you could
express very well with the DSL and at
the same time this has the benefit that
the architecture becomes a real artifact
in the software so you can actually say
okay so this is the semantics of our
architecture to iterate at this point
again usually architecture is something
people talk about or you know it draws
some power points and that stuff
architecture is not an artifact you can
use you can verify and if you do this in
a model driven way the architecture is
formalized and its tool usable because
if you build your concrete models of
your application something that some
people call the design an instance of
the architectural concepts then you can
use model validations and all other cool
things to verify that the model is
actually consistent with the
architecture so architecture becomes
executable and also you can add new
features to the architecture in a
well-defined way so what I'm wondering
is what do you think where is the
biggest benefit in this field I mean is
it just the first step towards an
architectural centric modern software
development or is the real benefit that
I should aim for to have a real
domain-specific language for the real
domain that I'm trying to model in the
real world of course the holy grail so
to speak is the real domain like
insurance or our automotive engine
control systems however considering
today's complexity in software
development which is you know tests more
or less awful platforms you have to
write a lot of glue code you have to do
all all these things to get your
business logic running so if you you if
you automate those technical aspects of
your project that's already a big
benefit actually I think many
organizations never go beyond this
architectural centric model of the
and that's fine if you have various
different domains which you all run on a
standard infrastructure with a standard
architecture like J to eat stuff then
it's quite quite feasible to come up
with a standardized architecture centric
metamodel and on top of that you you add
additional business logic and and and
different kinds of business logic for
which you don't want to provide
domain-specific languages so it's
perfectly okay to start with
architecture centric MDS D and never go
beyond it if you if you aim just at the
architecture architectural level the
next question would be do you think that
this should be standardized should there
be one way of doing say Java EE
architecture and a standardized
domain-specific language for this and
then reuse it in all projects because I
mean obviously this would mean that you
can reuse your implementation and
everything gets much cheaper and easier
and so what you're saying is that if you
come up with the metamodel and the
generators again again again and again
in each project then you always have the
effort of building these things over and
over again and that makes it more
expensive than it may be needed to be so
I mean yeah so it sounds like a good
idea to you know download this cartridge
for hibernate and spring and then you
just draw the pictures and everything is
fine and um maybe that's not really a
bad thing however what you lose is if
you just download the cartridge and
don't think about your own architecture
then you lose exactly that benefit which
is that building a generator helps you
understand what your architecture is all
about once a while ago I was trying to
build a generator that would generate an
editor based on eclipse GEF for
domain-specific metamodels so this was
actually one meta-level hire but that's
not important here so the the problem
was I had to understand to EF and G EF
is really not simple and I really had a
really hard time doing that and and I
tried to understand gf before starting
to build a generator for it and I gave
up on that I I just started building a
channel
because as soon as I understood
something about gef I coded that
knowledge into my generator so building
a generator helps you understand the
thing for which you built the generator
so and if you just download cartridge X
for technology Y then you you lose that
benefit on the other side being a
consultant I have that problem all the
time I have to reinvent the wheels in
many many projects and writing your
fifth generator for the fifth hibernate
mapping is obviously a boring thing so
there are really fundamental
technologies for which pre-built
cartridges of generator components are a
good thing so what I recommend in that
in that space is that you should use
those off-the-shelf cartridges but they
should be hidden from the actual
modelling so what you should do is you
should build your own meta model for
your architecture you should express
your architecture in that meta model
using DSL space in that meta model and
then use model to model transformations
to generate the input for the
off-the-shelf cartridges that you might
be able to download from somewhere so
the GAF example makes me wonder is this
again fixing a bad platform using a
generator because that's what we did
with extra plate and egb so do you think
that we could improve the infrastructure
like for example the graphical editing
framework or whatever and come up with
an infrastructure that is so good that
we don't need to have MD SD anymore and
we don't have to have any generators and
so on because everything works out quite
fine certainly I mean our platforms
today are far from from what we would
like them to be I mean many people bash
about j2ee although actually it's not
that bad but you have to write a lot of
stuff to get your things running so
writing better platforms will certainly
reduce the need for generating stuff
especially for those you know dump
generators that you know just generated
them glue code so for example if you
look at spring as a framework that you
could use as pay as a base for your
applications then the need to generate
stuff is certainly reduced so yeah to
some extent we need mdhd because our
platforms are bad however as soon as you
get really domain-specific so if your
meta model doesn't do the architecture
stuff anymore then there's this
discussion is kind of not relevant
anymore because you know the good
platforms don't help you with your
domain-specific things so if we stay in
the architectural centric mdhd space
even then it usually makes a lot of
sense to use generation on top of good
platforms because from if you do the
models right you can generate all kinds
of things starting from ant files over
package you know files that package your
applications test cases to some extent
at least you can generate all kinds of
artifacts that you that are outside the
scope of your execution platform another
thing is that if you for example if you
do component based design and you have a
model that expresses components and
their interfaces a second model that
expresses component instances and their
wirings and a third model that expresses
how those component instances are
deployed on system nodes
you know like processes and hosts
machines then you can generate all kinds
of things from that for example you can
you can generate all the code or all the
configuration that is needed to make
remote communication between components
located on two different processes
possible and even in spring this is a
something to do I mean you have to write
this configuration file you have to
provide all kinds of things it's not not
as bad as in j2ee
but having the well-separated spectrally
separated models that give you a good
overview and and consistently generating
the artifacts that you need is certainly
important so one last comment on that
even if you use something like spring
you still have to come up with non
runtime things such as for example
hibernate mappings and nobody automates
that for you so you have to generate
those so nobody will probably argue that
hibernate is a bad platform it's
probably quite good one for persistence
at least I don't know for better one but
you still need to generate those mapping
files so there is something to do
usually
ok so we've been discussing MDS D so far
and what I'm wondering of course is how
is this different from MDA because this
is obviously the big standard by the OMG
that also standardized this UML and
CORBA and everybody thought this this
was the next next big thing and now you
telling me that that MDS D is actually
the thing and the way to go so what's
the difference here
I think MDA is a specific flavor of
model driven development so what I'm
saying is MDS D defines you know things
like what's a model what's a meta model
what does the DSL how do they'll think
those those things go together how do
you generate stuff what's the difference
between architecture centric and and the
non architecture centric thing how do
you organize your development process so
that this approach actually works so
these kinds of things and the a is a
standardization initiative by the OMG
that tries to standardize some aspects
of that whole thing in order to you know
become tool interoperable and all those
other advantages of standards if they're
worked out well so specifically that
means that for example the OMG
standardize is meta meta model so that
would be the the meta model for building
metamodels so anyway it's important for
building tools that can exchange mdhd
artifacts and the this is called them
off the metal object facility so or
other things like for example for model
to model transformations the OMG has
just recently more or less finalized the
qvt
specification a standard for query views
and transformations they're also working
on a standardization of model to text so
their approach is not really different
it's just that they narrow down the
general approach to certain standards
and that could be important also
realistically speaking the MDA standard
in the past hasn't been very practically
useful so the MDA standards paper itself
is basically a vision statement and the
first rather concrete result of all
those standardization efforts is qvt and
also for qvt people are and don't
necessarily agree that what they
standardize is actually the right thing
MDA is certainly useful to standardize
certain aspects to make tool
interoperability become a reality but
the general thing is not something that
the the OMG trademarked may be one thing
OMG has always had a focus on
interoperability between runtime systems
that would be core
and between tools and so again in MDA
the focus was to become interoperable
between platforms so the idea is to
model your business logic and pimps
platform-independent models and then
transform that basically into using
various intermediate steps PS M's and
stuff to generate that into executable
code that can run on various platforms
so the cynics will say that
unfortunately not everybody kind of
standardized on OMGs platforms so now
the OMG is moving one level up and
standardized is the model layer so that
everybody can use their own platforms
but still people use oMG standard
development approaches one last thing in
practice using MDA tooling today means
that all your DSL czar basically UML
profiles that's not something that's
kind of written into the standard you
can use all kinds of tiers else based on
moth and the UML is is also based on
moth but in practice if you want to do
MDA with official MDA tools then that
means you have to render all your DSL as
UML profiles and that's something you
might like or not like some aspects of
your systems cannot reasonably be
modeled in UML and restricting yourself
to UML based DSL is not a good thing in
general and as we pointed out there are
also a textural IDs else and that's just
something that you can't do with UML so
it's not really useful to limit yourself
there so then if if MDA and the MDA
tools are not the thing that you should
generally use then the next question
obviously would be which tooth should I
use and which other options are there
that I can have a look at so can you
give an overview about those so the idea
of using domain-specific languages to
make development more efficient and
automating the transformation into
executable code is is not specific to
MDA and MDS D there are various industry
initiatives that look at that
historically generative programming you
might know the black book with a white
cat on it from Christopher charnetski
and echo generative programming
basically aims at the same thing you
have specifications and your trans
from them into optimized products so
same idea also if you look at
domain-specific visual modeling that's
something that has been used for a while
there is a company called medicaid's
from finland evitable called meta at it
and they've been using this approach for
a long time so it's not new it has
become a hype topic because of m of
omg's MDA so that's something that has
to be said positively about MDA it has
brought this approach into kind of
everybody's mind other folks like for
example Microsoft are also working on it
they call their approach software
factories software factories are not
just about using DSL it's generally
about domain-specific product line
engineering things and there are other
aspects to that than just these else but
these else are an important part and
then there are things like for example
the language or in the programming thing
from the IntelliJ folks is that their
name no JetBrains JetBrains is the
company name they're building a tool of
the mouth the meta programming system so
this is kind of everybody's hobby at
this time now if you want to start today
you have to be a bit pragmatic and you
have to select your tools of course you
can use UML tools as one way of building
tiers else and then you have to use some
kind of transformer or generator
framework that is after you wrote the
UML model to an XML file
you can then read that X Amaya and
generate code so that's a standard
approach and there are various tools
there is obviously have to say open
architecture where I'm committed in this
project there is an 2m they are there is
various commercial tools that do that by
the way you shouldn't use XSLT
transformations or JSP engines that
doesn't scale so but then if you look a
bit further and you want to do
sophisticated model to model
transformations or build your own
graphical editors you should definitely
have a look at the Eclipse world on
Eclipse there is the GMT project stands
for generative model transformer and
that's a kind of container project for
all kinds of other projects there are
there's the model to model
transformation engine ATL there is open
architecture is actually a part of that
project now and there are other
projects that aim at managing big models
and then there is also a very
interesting thing which is called EMF
which is the Eclipse modeling framework
which is actually also a meta meta model
one that is a subset of OMGs muff we
won't go into details here anyway it's
it's much simpler than the muff and most
of those eclipse-based mdhd tools
actually built on top of EMF for those
who are interested open architecture
where four also uses EMF a very very
interesting upcoming project is the gmf
project and that's a project that allows
you to generate graphical modeling
editors from a meta model expressed in
eclipse EMF so you build your domain
metamodeling EMF add a couple of
configuration models not going to go
into details here and then you press a
button and what you get is an eclipse
plug-in that contains a graphical editor
graphical in the sense of boxes and
rectangles and these kinds of things to
build instances of your domain-specific
metamodel and that's really cool because
if i look at projects today the problem
is not that I need functional highly
sophisticated transformational languages
such as QT what I need is small tailored
specific editors to express my models
and that's where gmf is going to be a
big big win this concludes this first
part of the discussion of MDS D in the
next episode we'll talk about some less
technical issues such as the
relationship of MDS D and agility MDS D
and offshoring as well as how to
introduce MDS D into your projects
thanks for listening and hope you're
back next time
[Music]
this was another episode of software
engineering radio for general
information feedback and past episodes
go to se - radio net software
engineering radio wants to thank Henning
poorly for providing the music views in
the show